Partial Guide to the Memorial Library of Music Collection
Department of Special Collections
- Giroflé girofla. / LECOCQ, ALEXANDRE CHARLES (1832-1918), MLM 587
  Opéra-bouffe en 3 acres. Paroles de MM. A. Vanloo & E. Leterrier. Musique de Charles Lecocq. Partition chant & piano arrangée par Léon Roques. Paris, Brandus [1874] Pl. no. B. & Cie. 11,952, 11,950. First edition. Inscribed to Titus-Charles Constantin by the composer.
- La petite Mariée. / LECOCQ, ALEXANDRE CHARLES (1832-1918), MLM 588
  Paroles de MM. E. Leterrier & A. Vanloo. Musique de Charles Lecocq. Partition chant & piano, arrangée par Léon Roques. Paris, Brandus [1875] Pl. no. B. & Cie. 12078. First edition.
- Plutus. / LECOCQ, ALEXANDRE CHARLES (1832-1918), MLM 589
  Opéra comique en trois actes. Poème de MM. Albert Millaud & Gaston Jollivet. Musique de Charles Lecocq. Partition chant et piano réduite par A. Bazille. Paris, Brandus [ca. 1886] Pl. no. B. & Cie. 13083. First edition. Presented for the first time at Paris, March 31, 1886.
- Le pompon. / LECOCQ, ALEXANDRE CHARLES (1832-1918), MLM 590
  Opéra comique en 3 acres. Paroles de MM. H. Chivot & A. Duru. Musique de Charles Lecocq. Partition chant & piano, arrangée par Léon Roques. Paris, Brandus [ca. 1875] Pl. no. B. & Cie. 12050. First edition. Presented for the first time at Paris, November 10, 1875. Inserted is an autograph letter signed. To an unknown correspondent [Paris] January4, 1891 [Inserted in item no. 591.]
- La Princesse des Canaries. / LECOCQ, ALEXANDRE CHARLES (1832-1918), MLM 591
  Opéra bouffe en 3 actes de Chivot et Duru. Musique de Ch. Lecocq. Partition chant et piano transcrite par Léon Roques. Paris, Choudens Père & Fils [1883] Pl. no. A. C. 5797. First edition. Inscribed to Mlle. Jeanne Andrée by the composer. Mlle. Andrée sang the role of Inès in the first performance at the Théâtre des Folies Dramatiques, Paris, February 9, 1883.
- Nephté. / LEMOYNE,JEANBAPTISTE(1751-1796), MLM 592
  Tragédie en trois actes, représentée pour la première fois, par l'Académie Royale de Musique, le mardi 15 décembre 1789. Mise en musique par M. Le Moyne. Paris, chez l'auteur [ca. 1790] First edition. Orchestral score. The text is by Hoffman. Wotquenne, 1722.
- Chatterton. / LEONCAVALLO, RUGGIERO (1858-1919), MLM 593
  Dramma lirico in tre atti. Parole e musica di Ruggero [sic] Leoncavallo. Opera completa per canto e pianoforte. Riduzione dell' autore. Bologna, Achille Tedeschi, c1896. Pl. no. A. 3000 T. First edition. This opera was accepted for production at Bologna, but the impresario absconded. It was finally presented at Rome, March 10, 1896.
- I Medici. / LEONCAVALLO, RUGGIERO (1858-1919), MLM 594
  Azione storica in quattro atti. Parole e musica di R. Leoncavallo. Riduzione per canto e pianoforte. Milano, Edoardo Sonzogno, c1893. Pl. no. E 833 S. First edition. This is the first part of a projected trilogy. The other parts, Savonarola and Cesare Borgia, were never completed.
- Autograph letter signed. / LEONCAVALLO, RUGGIERO (1858-1919), MLM 594A
  To ""Paolo,"" Brissago, October 23, 1901.
- Pagliacci. / LEONCAVALLO, RUGGIERO (1858-1919), MLM 595
  Dramma in due atti. Parole e musica di R. Leoncavallo. Riduzione per canto e pianoforte. Milano, Edoardo Sonzogno, c1892. Pl. no. E. 654 S. First edition. Inscribed by the composer. Presented for the first time at Milan, May 21, 1892.
- Paillasse. / LEONCAVALLO, RUGGIERO (1858-1919), MLM 596
  Drame lyrique en deux actes de R. Leoncavallo. Partition chant et piano. Paris, Choudens Fils, c1893. Pl. no. A. C. 9819 on p. 1, A. C. 9712 on p. 2-24, and none on p. 25-204. First edition. Inserted is a photograph signed by the composer together with two bars from the score. Inscribed by the composer to M. Rohrbach, October 10, 1902.
- Zaza. / LEONCAVALLO, RUGGIERO (1858-1919), MLM 597
  Comedic lyrique en quatre actes. Poésie et musique de R. Leoncavallo. Tirée de la comédie de P. Berton et Ch. Simon. Répresentée pour la première fois, au Théâtre Lyrique International de Milan, le 10 novembre 1900. Transcription pour chant et piano. Milan, Edouard Sonzogno, c1900. Pl. no. E 1052 S. First edition. Inscribed to Mme. Edwards by the composer. The inscription includes three bars of music with text from the score.
- Zingari. / LEONCAVALLO, RUGGIERO (1858-1919), MLM 598
  Dramma lirico in due episodi di E. Cavacchioli e G. Emanuel. Ridiuzione per canto e pianoforte dell'autore. Milano, Edoardo Sonzogno, c1972. Pl. no. E 1767 S. At head of title: R. Leoncavallo. First edition. Inscribed by the composer. The inscription includes five bars from the score. The libretto is based on the poem by Pushkin. Text in Italian and German. Presented for the first time at London, 1912.
- Le chemineau. / LEROUX, XAVIER HENRY NAPOLEON (1863-1919), MLM 599
  Drame lyrique en quatre actes de Jean Richepin. Musique de Xavier Leroux. Partition chant et piano. Paris, Choudens, c1907. Pl. no. A. C. 13489. First edition. Inscribed to Mme. Vuillaume by the composer. Presented for the first time at Paris, November 6, 1907.
- Le nil. / LEROUX, XAVIER HENRY NAPOLEON (1863-1919), MLM 600
  Poésie d'Armand Renaud. Musique de Xavier Leroux. Rémineur. pour chant avec acct. de violon et de piano. Paris, Heugel [ca. 1896] Pl. no. H. et Cie. 7824 (1) First edition. Inscribed by the composer.
- La nuit consolatrice. / LEROUX, XAVIER HENRY NAPOLEON (1863-1919), MLM 601
  Sonnet de Ferdinand Hérold. Musique de Xavier Leroux. Pour baryton ou mezzo-soprano avec acct. de piano [et] avec acct.de violon et de piano. Paris, Heugel, c1898. Pl. no. H. & Cie. 19247 (1 bis & 1 ter) First edition. Inscribed by the composer.
- Musique de scène pour Les Perses. / LEROUX, XAVIER HENRY NAPOLEON (1863-1919), MLM 602
  Tragédie d'Eschyle. Traduction française de A. F. Hérold. Paris, Alphonse Leduc, c1896. Pl. no. A. L. 9718. First edition. Inscribed to René Lara by the composer.
- La reine fiammette. / LEROUX, XAVIER HENRY NAPOLEON (1863-1919), MLM 603
  Conte dramatique en quatre actes et six tableaux de Catulle Mendès. Musique de Xavier Leroux. Partition chant et piano. Paris, Choudens, c1903. Pl. no. A. C. 12,550. First edition. Inscribed by the composer. Presented for the first time in Paris, December 23, 1903.
- Venus et Adonis. / LEROUX, XAVIER HENRY NAPOLEON (1863-1919), MLM 604
  Scène lyrique. Poème de L. de Gramont. Musique de Xavier Leroux. Paris, Alphonse Leduc, c1897. Pl. no. A. L. 9657. First edition. Inscribed to A. C. Bellaigue by the composer.
- Cantate religieuse suivie du motet: Veni sponsa coronaberis. Soli & choeurs. / LESUEUR, JEAN FRANCOIS (1760-1837), MLM 605
  Composée et dédiée à la Société Philharmonique de Londres par Le Sueur. 13me livraison. Paris, Beauvais [ca. 1818] Pl. no. 13. Orchestral score. First edition. Inscribed to Gounod by the composqr. Inserted is a slip with Gounod's signature.
- Première messe solennelle à grande orchestre. / LESUEUR, JEAN FRANCOIS (1760-1837), MLM 606
  Composée et dédiée à Mr le Duc de Gramont. par Lesueur. avec accompagnement l'orgue ou de piano par Ermel. Ire livraison. Paris, J. Frey [ca. 1828] First edition. Inscribed to Gounod by the composer.
- Autograph letter signed. / LESUEUR, JEAN FRANCOIS (1760-1837), MLM 606A
  To M. Delaferté, n. p., January 23,1814. A long letter (four closely written pages). The composer tabulates the amounts he receives from his official appointments and compares these sums with those received by his confrères. He protests against a proposed reduction of his emoluments from a figure of 18,000 to one which he says would bring him only 6,000 francs, less than he received when he was twenty-three, as composer and Master of the Chapel of the Metropole, Paris, which was worth 10,000 francs, when living was much cheaper. This letter has a contemporary ring to it.
- Rachel. / LESUEUR, JEAN FRANCOIS (1760-1837), MLM 607
  Oratorio historique et prophétique à grands choeurs & à gd. orchestre, avec soli, composé par LeSueur. 7me livraison. Paris, J. Frey [ca. 183-] First edition. Inscribed to Gounod by the composer. Text in Latin. Wotquenne, 1088.
- La rôtisserie de la reine pédauque. / LEVADE, CHARLES GASTON (1868-), MLM 608
  Comédie lyrique en 4 actes et 5 tableaux d'après le roman d'Anatole France par Georges Docquois. Partition pour piano et chant, réduite par l'auteur. Paris, Enoch, c1919. At head of title: Charles Levadé. Pl. no. E. & C. 7847. First edition. Inscribed to M. Chéreau by the composer.
- Die Legende von der heiligen Elisabeth. / LISZT, FRANZ (1811-1886), MLM 609
  Oratorium nach Worten von Otto Roquette, componirt von Franz Liszt. Klavier-Auszug. Leipzig, C. F. Kahnt [1869] Pl. no. 1156. First edition.
- Autograph note signed. / LISZT, FRANZ (1811-1886), MLM 609A
  To an unidentified correspondent, n. p., [April?] 1868. Also inserted is an engraved portrait of the composer by McRae. [1841?][London].
- Missa pro organo lectarum celebrationi missarum adjumento inserviens. / LISZT, FRANZ (1811-1886), MLM 610
  Messe pour orgue servant d'accompagnement à la célébration des messes basses. Roma, P. Manganelli, 1879. Pl. no. P. 446 M. First edition. Inscribed to Hermann Dimmler by the composer.
- Autograph note signed. / LISZT, FRANZ (1811-1886), MLM 610A
  To an unidentified correspondent, n. p. [dated later than 1865]. This is of particular California interest. It reads: ""In San Fran (Californien) würde kürzlich Liszt's Ungarische Krönungs-messe (Soli, Chor, und Orchester) unter Leitung der Herrn Director Dohrmann ausgeführt. [Also a portrait of the composer.] [Les préludes. See Symphonische Dichtungen für grosses Orchester. No. 3. Les préludes.
- Prometheus. / LISZT, FRANZ (1811-1886), MLM 611
  Chöre zu Herder's ""Entfesseltem Prometheus"" von Franz Liszt. Verbindender Text von Richard Pohl. Partitur. Neue Auflage. Leipzig, C. F. Kahnt [1876] Pl. no. 1951. First engraved edition. Inscribed to Saint-Saëns by the composer.
- Psalm 129. ""De profundis clamavi,"" Aus der Tiefe rufe ich""; für eine ""Bass-oder Altstimme und Pianoforte-oder Orgelbegleitung." / LISZT, FRANZ (1811-1886), MLM 612
  Componirt von Franz Liszt. Leipzig, C. F. Kahnt [1886] Pl. no. 2593. Inscribed to Marianne Brandt by the composer.
- Symphonische Dichtungen für grosses Orchester. / LISZT, FRANZ (1811-1886), MLM 613
  Partitur. No. 3. Les préludes (nach Lamartine). Leipzig, Breitkopf & Härtel [1856] Pl. no. 9056. At head of title: F. Liszt. First edition.
- Grande valse di bravura pour le piano à quatre-mains, dédiée à son ami P. Wolff par F. Liszt." / LISZT, FRANZ (1811-1886), MLM 614
  Op. 6. Paris, Bernard Little, 1856. Pl. no. B. L. 1205. First edition. Inscribed by the composer. See also BERTIN, LOUISE ANGELIQUE (1805-1877). See also Bülow, Hans Guido, Freiherr Von (1830-1894) (Mazurka-fantaisie, op. 13. Original manuscript of Liszt's transcription for orchestra.
- Concerto symphonique no. v. Op. 123. / LITOLFF, HENRY CHARLES (1818-1891), MLM 615
  Braunschweig, Henry Litolff [1878] Pl. no. 2588. First edition. Inscribed to Chabrillon by the composer.
- [Die Heilung des Blindgeborene, opus 131]." / LOEWE, JOHANN KARL GOTTFRIED (1796-1869), MLM 616
  Original manuscript signed. ca. 1861. Full score for alto recitative, four-part chorus, and organ or piano. 18 leaves (34 pages) 27 x 34cm. (1 leaf, 27 x 241/2 cm.) Inserted at end is a sheet with directions for the engraver.
- Little grey home in the West. / LOHR, HERMANN, MLM 617
  Piano and vocal score. Text by D. Eardley-Wilmot. Original manuscript signed. 4 leaves (title-page, 3 pages) 241/2 x 301/2 cm. This was one of the most popular ballads of the century.
- Czaar und Zimmermann oder die beiden Peter, komische Oper in drei v Acten von G. A. Lortzing." / LORTZING, GUSTAV ALBERT (1801-1851), MLM 618
  Vollständiger Clavierauszug. Leipzig, Breitkopf und Härtel [1837] Plate no. 5817. First edition. Presented for the first time at Leipzig, December 22, 1837. Wotquenne, 3522.
- Autograph note signed. / LORTZING, GUSTAV ALBERT (1801-1851), MLM 618A
  To an unidentified correspondent, n. p., January 22, 1843.
- Amadis, tragédie, mise en musique par Monsieur de Lully." / LULLY,JEAN BAPTISTE (1632-1687), MLM 619
  Paris, Christophe Ballard, 1684. First edition. Orchestral score. The text is by Philippe Quinault. Presented for the first time at Paris, January 18, 1684. Wolffheim, II, 1474; Wotquenne, 1749.
- Armide, tragédie mise en musique par Monsieur de Lully." / LULLY,JEAN BAPTISTE (1632-1687), MLM 620
  Paris, Christopher Ballard, 1686. First edition. Orchestral score. The text is by Philippe Quinault. Presented for the first time at Paris, February 15, 1686. Wotquenne, 1752.
- Phaeton. / LULLY,JEAN BAPTISTE (1632-1687), MLM 620A
  Paris, 1683.
- Proserpine, tragédie mise en musique par Monsieur de Lully, surintendant de la musique de Roy." / LULLY,JEAN BAPTISTE (1632-1687), MLM 621
  Paris, Christophe Ballard, 1680. First edition. Orchestral score. The text is by Philippe Quinault. Presented for the first time at Saint-Germain en Laye, February 3, 1680. Eitner, VI, 245; Wolffheim, II, 1488; Wotquenne, 1741.
- Document signed by the composer. / LULLY,JEAN BAPTISTE (1632-1687), MLM 621A
  November 26, 1686. A receipt on vellum for 1,200 livres received from M. Baudouin, Trésorier Payeur des Gages de Messieurs les Conseillers Secrétaires de Sadite Majesté.
- Les adieus. / LVOFF, ALEXIS FEODOROVICH (1799-1870), MLM 622
  Hymne composé à l'occasion de la sortie des élèves de l'institut patriotique à St. Petersbourg, par A. Lvoff. Original manuscript signed. 6 leaves (11 pages) 291/2 x 241/2 cm. Complete score. Lvoff is best known for his arrangement of Giardini's ""God Save the Czar,"" the Imperial Russian national anthem.
- [Russian national anthem] / LVOFF, ALEXIS FEODOROVICH (1799-1870), MLM 623
  Original manuscript signed. 1833. 7 leaves (12 pages) 241/2 x 31 cm. The manuscript of Lvoff's arrangement of Giardini's ""God Save the Czar,"" the Imperial Russian national anthem. Inscribed to C. Lipinski, March 2, 1834.
- 3e symphonie. / MAGNARD,ALBERIC(1865-1914), MLM 624
  Partition d'orchestre. Paris, L'auteur, c1902. At head of title: Albéric Magnard. First edition. Inscribed to M. P. Poujaud by the composer.
- Funf Kindertotenlieder. / MAHLER, GUSTAV (1860-1911), MLM 625
  Words by Rückert. Music by Gustav Mahler. Leipzig, C. F. Kahnt, C1905. Pl. nos. 4459, a-e. Caption-title. Proof-sheets with the composer's corrections throughout and inscribed to Frau Edytha Moser by him. Contents: No. 1. ""Nun will die Sonn' so hell aufgeh'n""; No. 2. ""Nun seh' ich wohl, warum so dunkle Flammen""; No. 3. ""Wenn dein Mütterlein""; No. 4. ""Oft denk' ich, sie sind nur ausgegangen!""; No. 5. ""In diesem Wetter!"" These famous and moving songs on the death of a child are here in a unique proof copy as sent to the publisher. Frau Moser was the wife of Kolo Moser. Both were members of the Vienna ""Secession"" and intimate friends of the composer.
- Ich bin der Welt abhanden gekommen. / MAHLER, GUSTAV (1860-1911), MLM 626
  (Rückert) [Musik von] Gustav Mahler. Leipzig, C. F. Kahnt, C1905. Pl. no. 4473. Caption-title. Proof-sheets of the first edition with a title-page, inscription to Frau Edytha Moser, and a few corrections in the composer's handwriting.
- Lieder und Gesänge für eine Singstimme und Klavier. von Gustav Mahler. / MAHLER, GUSTAV (1860-1911), MLM 627
  Heft I für hohe Stimme. Mainz, B. Schott's Söhne [1885] P1. no. 25183. First edition. Inscribed: ""Alte Bekante und Neue Gesandte leget zu Fussen mit freundlichen Grüssen der-unter Genante! Hamburg 8 Februar 92."" Contents: 1, ""Frülingsmorgen"" (R. Leander); 2, ""Erinnerung"" (R. Leander); 3, ""Hans und Grethe"" (Volkslied); 4, ""Serenade aus 'Don Juan'"" (Tirso de Molina); 5, ""Phantasie aus 'Don Juan'"" (Tirso de Molina).
- Symphonie in C moll No. 2 von Gustav Mahler. / MAHLER, GUSTAV (1860-1911), MLM 628
  Clavierauszug à 4 ms. arrangirt v. Bruno Walter. Wien, Josef Weinberger [c1895] Pl. no. 3. First edition. Inscribed by the composer. With this is bound the Chor-Particelle, 1, 2, 3, 4, Satz tacet, 5, Satz tacet bis: Der grosse Appell. Pl. no.4. The ""Resurrection"" symphony. Performed for the first time at Berlin, March 4, 1895, with Richard Strauss conducting.
- 3 Symphonie von Gustav Mahler. / MAHLER, GUSTAV (1860-1911), MLM 629
  Partitur. Wien, Josef Weinberger [1896] Pl. no. 9. First edition. With corrections in red ink by the composer. The corrections were incorporated into the Universal Edition of the score.
- [Symphony-no. 3, D minor]" / MAHLER, GUSTAV (1860-1911), MLM 630
  Original manuscript. 1893. 2 leaves (4pages) 27 x 351/2 cm. In a wrapper made from a folio signature of music paper. On front wrapper: ""Steinbach am Attersee. Am 28 Juli 1896 ereignete sich das Seltsame, dass ich meiner lieben Freundin Natalie den Kern eines Baumes schenken konnte, der trotzdem aber in voller Lebensgrösse mit allen Zweigen, Blättern und Früchten nun in die Welt hinein blüht und wächst. Gustav Mahler."" Important sketches for the 3d Symphony.
- [Symphony no. 3, D minor]" / MAHLER, GUSTAV (1860-1911), MLM 631
  Original manuscript 1895. 4 leaves (7pages) 27 x 351/2 cm. This has the title ""Was das Kind erzählt."" It is a sketch for the first and second movements. ""Merkwürdig, ist dass ein Blatt aus dem Nachlass der Verfasserin unter der Ueberschrift 'Was das Kind erzählt' die Skizzen zum Blumensatz enthält"" (Bauer-Lechner, Erinnerungen an G. Mahler, Leipzig, 1923, p. 20). These sketches are from Natalie Bauer's papers.
- Symphonie in G dur No. 4 von Gustav Mahler. / MAHLER, GUSTAV (1860-1911), MLM 632
  Partitur. Wien, Ludwig Doblinger [1900] Cover-title. Pl. no. 31. First edition. With signature of Richard Specht. Page of original manuscript - ""Skizzenblatt"" (cf. separate entry) See item no. 633.
- [Symphony no.4, G major]" / MAHLER, GUSTAV (1860-1911), MLM 633
  Original manuscript, ""Skizzenblatt' ca. 1900. 1 leaf (1 page) 341/2 x 261/2 cm. Authenticated on first page by Alma Maria Mahler. Inserted in the first edition of the score.
- Symphonie No. 5 für grosses Orchester von Gustav Mahler. / MAHLER, GUSTAV (1860-1911), MLM 634
  Partitur. Leipzig C. F. Peters [1905] Pl. no. 9015. First edition. Inscribed to Hermann Behn by the composer. Presented for the first time at Cologne, October 18, 1904.
- A Treatise of Musick. / Malcom, A., MLM 634A
- San Francesco d'Assisi, mistero." / MALIPIERO, G. FRANCESCO (1882-), MLM 635
  London, J. et W. Chester, 1921. No. 161 of an edition limited to 250 copies, signed by the composer.
- Songs in the new opera call'd Hydaspes as they are perform'd at the Queens Theatre. / MANCINI, FRANCESCO (1679-1739), MLM 636
  [London] I. Walsh and I. Hare [1710] First edition. Cf. Smith, Bibliography of musical works published by John Walsh, 354, p. 109. [Bound with item no. 118, shelved under Bononcini.]
- Aria. / MANDANICI, PLACIDO (1798-1852), MLM 637
  Original manuscript signed. 13 leaves (26 pages) 271/2 x 201/2 cm. A finely written manuscript of an opera aria in the key of C major and containing 101 measures. The tenor is called Cavaliere. The coloratura ""fireworks"" as well as the orchestration indicate the composer to be a follower of Rossini. Mandanici was a pupil of Raimondi and wrote many operas and church music.
- Credo a 3 voci con orchestra. / MANNA, RUGGIERO (1808-1864), MLM 638
  Original manuscript signed. 1828. 39 leaves (77 pages) 311/2 x 21 cm. An interesting autograph of a contemporary of Rossini, Donizetti, Bellini, and Verdi. A native of Trieste, Manna became a pupil of Vincenzo Lavigna, the teacher of Verdi. As a boy of fo
- La Première Pierre de l'Eglise d'Argis. / Manry, Charles, MLM 638A
  Legende Valaque. Paroles de Mr. Antoni Deshamps. Op. 56. Partition piano et chant. [Paris] France musicals [18..].
- Der Bäbu. / MARSCHNER, HEINRICH AUGUST (1795-1861), MLM 639
  Komische Oper in drei Acten von W. A. Wohlbrück in Musik gesetzt von Heinrich Marschner. 98s. Werk. Vollständiger Clavierauszug vom Componisten. Leipzig, Julius Wunder [ca. 1838] Pl. no. J. W. 73. First edition. Fragment of manuscript, 1842, of an unidentified composition for piano (cf. separate entry.) See item no. 642.
- Kaiser Adolph von Nassau. / MARSCHNER, HEINRICH AUGUST (1795-1861), MLM 640
  Grosse Oper in 4 Acten von Herbert Rau. In Musik gesetz von Dr. Heinrich Marschner. 130tes. Werk. Vollständiger Clavierauszug von Componisten. Hannover, C. Bachmann [1845] Pl. no. 200. First edition. Presented for the first time at Hanover, in 1843. Inserted is a contemporary manuscript giving the cast and contents. Wotquenne, 3523.
- Der Vampyr. / MARSCHNER, HEINRICH AUGUST (1795-1861), MLM 641
  Grosse romantische Oper in zwei Akten von W. H. Wohlbrück, in Musik gesetzt und Sr. Durchlaucht Carl regierendem Herzoge von Braunschweig-Lüneberg. In tiefster Ehrfurcht zugeeignet von Heinr. Marschner. Vollständiger Klavierauszug vom Componisten. 42s. Werk. Leipzig, Friedrich Hofmeister [1828] Pl. no. 1356 a-b. First edition. Presented for the first time at Leipzig, March 28, 1828.
- Autograph letter signed. / MARSCHNER, HEINRICH AUGUST (1795-1861), MLM 641A
  To an unidentified conductor, Leipzig, May 1, 1828, Marschner discusses Der Vampyr which promises to become a great box-office success. (Also postcard portrait.)
- Manuscript fragment. / MARSCHNER, HEINRICH AUGUST (1795-1861), MLM 642
  1842. 1 leaf (1 page) 24 x 281/2 cm. (Eight bars of an unidentified composition for piano. In the first edition of the piano and vocal score of Der Bäbu.
- [Canons] / MARTINI, GIOVANNI BATTISTA (""PADRE MARTINI"") (1706-1784), MLM 643
  302 canons for various voices. Original manuscript. 70 leaves (136 pages of music, 4 pages of index). [Martini] had a predilection for the canons He [is said to have composed not less than 1,273. The importance of this manuscript is obvious since some 240 of these canons have never been published.] There is a remarkable diversity in the text and music. Although a few of the canons are serious, the greater number are humorous and gay reflecting the life of Bologna as Martini observed it.
- Ave Maris. / MARTINI, GIOVANNI BATTISTA (""PADRE MARTINI"") (1706-1784), MLM 644
  Original manuscript signed. n.d. 1 leaf (2 pages) 161/2 x 221/2 cm. ""Padre Martini"" was the foremost Italian musicologist and musical theorist of the eighteenth century.
- Duo pour violon e violoncelle. / Martinu, Bohuslav (1890-), MLM 645
  Paris, La Sirène Musicale [c1928] Pl. no. S. M. 144. At head of title: Bohuslav Martinu. First edition. Inscribed to Henri Prunières by the composer.
- Sketches to string sextette. Dedicated to Mrs. E. Sprague Coolidge. / Martinu, Bohuslav (1890-), MLM 646
  Original manuscript signed. 7 leaves (14 pages) 27 x 351/2 cm.
- 2a sinfonia a grande orchestra (in fa maggiore) di Giuseppe Martucci. / MARTUCCI, GIUSEPPE (1856-1909), MLM 647
  Op. 81. Partitura. Milano, G. Ricordi [1906] Pl. no. 1. First edition. Inscribed to Arthur Pougin by the composer.
- Cavalleria rusticana. / MASCAGNI, PIETRO (1863-1946), MLM 648
  Original manuscript. 1890. 139 leaves (277 pages) 271/2 x 39 cm. [This is the actual manuscript which Mascagni submitted to the Milan music publisher Sonzogno] in the second contest established by him [and has at the end the Milan prefectural certificate
- Cavalleria rusticana. / MASCAGNI, PIETRO (1863-1946), MLM 649
  Melodramma in un atto di G. Targioni-Tozzetti e G. Menasci. Musica di Pietro Mascagni. Riduzione per canto e pianoforte di Leopoldo Mugnone. Roma, Sonzogno, c1890. Pl. no. E. 492S. First edition. Inscribed to Ignazio Alfano by the composer.
- (1) a contemporary print of Mme. Gemma Bellincioni, the first Santuzza, inscribed for the collection, and (2) a photograph of Mme. Emma Eames in the role of Santuzza at the Metropolitan Opera House, 1891-1892, inscribed for the collection." / MASCAGNI, PIETRO (1863-1946), MLM 649A
- 7 photographs of Emma Eames. / MASCAGNI, PIETRO (1863-1946), MLM 649B
  n.d.